https://youtu.be/GCaxUeawaW0
.
PAUL CUBBON: I've touched on the difference between pricing strategy
Tôi đã nhắc qua về sự khác biệt giữa các chiến lược giá
and pricing tactics a couple of times.
và chiến thuật giá một vài lần rồi.
And I want to just give you some examples that
Tôi sẽ đưa ra một số ví dụ
will allow you to see the difference between doing something where you're
cho thấy sự khác biệt
in charge-- you're setting the strategy and then the tactics cascade
giữa việc vạch ra chiến lược
down as ways of implementing that strategy-- versus where you are
và các chiến thuật để thực hiện chiến lược đó
tactically and sometimes almost automatically reacting
so với việc phản ứng thụ động
to somebody else and their strategy.
trước chiến lược của người khác.
How to think about it?
Nói thế nào nhỉ?
Do you want to set the strategy and then implement through your tactics?
Bạn muốn thiết lập chiến lược và thực thi nó bằng chiến thuật của mình?
Or do you want your tactics to actually reflect your reaction
Hay bạn muốn chiến thuật của mình
to someone else's strategy?
đáp lại chiến lược của người khác?
It's a key point.
Đó là điểm mấu chốt.
So let me take this forward for you.
Để tôi làm rõ thêm.
Whether you are leading or reacting to others on pricing in the marketplace,
Bạn muốn là người định giá hay là người phản ứng lại mức giá của người khác
is a key thing to consider.
trên thị trường là điều phải cân nhắc.
The next thing that relates to that is, what are your objectives
Tiếp theo, mục tiêu của bạn là gì
if you are going to change pricing?
khi thay đổi mức giá?
So I want you to consider the following.
Tôi muốn bạn xem xét như sau.
This line here represents time.
Đường thẳng này thể hiện thời gian.
And what typically happens is if our volume is steady over time here
Khi doanh số đang ổn định theo thời gian,
and then we actually discount our pricing,
và chúng ta tiến hành giảm giá
when we discount our pricing at this stage
ở giai đoạn này,
here, then what we typically see, we would expect,
ta thường kỳ vọng
if the sensitivity of the purchaser to the discounted price is sufficient,
sự nhạy cảm với giá của người mua hàng
we'll see our volume go up.
sẽ làm tăng doanh số.
So our volume goes up like that.
Doanh số tăng lên như thế này.
And then what happens when here we bring our pricing back up
Sẽ thế nào nếu ta tăng giá trở lại
to where it was before?
mức ban đầu?
Well, the volume comes down like this.
Doanh số sẽ giảm thế này.
And then, unfortunately in this situation,
Và rồi, thật không may,
we see almost a mirror image of our volume gain in a volume loss.
ta thấy hình ảnh của tăng doanh số trong giảm doanh số.
So what's happened here?
Chuyện gì đang xảy ra?
How do we make sense of this?
Hiểu thế nào đây?
We discounted the price.
Ta giảm giá.
Why?
Tại sao?
Because maybe we thought more people were going to buy.
Có thể ta nghĩ sẽ có thêm nhiều người mua.
What's happened here is either our existing loyal customers
Thực tế thì có thể các khách hàng trung thành hiện tại
have stockpiled a brand they were prepared
đã nhân cơ hội giảm giá
to pay full price for at a lower price.
để mua tích lũy sản phẩm.
Have you ever found yourself doing that?
Bạn có từng làm như thế chưa?
Going in and buying five boxes of cereal or five boxes of cookie?
Đi siêu thị và mua hẳn năm hộp ngũ cốc hay năm hộp bánh quy?
They're your favorite cookies, and wow, they gave them away to you.
Đó là loại bánh quy bạn thích, và kìa, giá giảm rẻ như cho.
And so you have paid less for them.
Và bạn trả tiền ít hơn.
The company's made less money.
Công ty nhận được ít hơn.
Or the alternative scenario is that people who weren't your customers
Hay một trường hợp khác là những người không phải khách hàng của bạn
tried you, but they only tried you because you were cheap.
dùng thử sản phẩm, nhưng họ thử chỉ vì bạn bán rẻ.
And after they tried you, whatever they thought of you,
Nhưng điều đó không đủ để thuyết phục họ
it wasn't enough to pay the regular price.
mua với mức giá thông thường.
So that's the first situation.
Đó là tình huống đầu tiên.
Typically, it's not a good scenario.
Thường đây không phải là kịch bản tốt.
And if you do it repeatedly, what you're doing is you're cheapening your brand.
Nếu bạn làm thế liên tục, bạn đang giảm giá trị thương hiệu.
You're diluting your margin.
Bạn đang làm giảm lợi nhuận biên.
And you're educating your potential customers,
Và bạn đang khuyến khích khách hàng tiềm năng,
even your ones that like you, to wait until you are on discount
ngay cả những người ủng hộ bạn, đợi đến lúc giảm giá
before they buy from you.
mới mua hàng.
So let's look at a second scenario.
Ta sẽ xem kịch bản thứ hai.
A second scenario is this one, and we can go more quickly now.
Với kịch bản hai này, ta sẽ đi nhanh hơn.
And basically, it goes like this.
Căn bản là thế này.
So this is where the price goes down, and this
Đây là lúc giá giảm,
is where the price comes back up.
đây là lúc giá tăng trở lại.
And so we're getting some additional volume.
Và ta tăng thêm được doanh số.
But really, we've either got our existing customers stockpiling,
Nhưng thực tế, hoặc là ta đã thuyết phục khách hàng hiện tại mua dự trữ,
but they consumed more or they gave it away to friends, whatever it may be,
họ sử dụng nhiều hơn, đem cho, tặng,
or we brought in some new customers to trial us.
hoặc là ta thu hút được khách hàng mới dùng thử.
They quite liked it, but they weren't prepared to carry on.
Họ thích, nhưng chưa sẵn sàng mua tiếp.
What we really want to do is this third scenario.
Cái ta hướng đến là kịch bản thứ ba.
We want to do something like this.
Ta muốn thực tế như sau.
So what's happening over time is this is when our discounted price came in.
Đây là khi chúng ta giảm giá.
This is when our price came back to normal.
Còn đây là khi giá quay lại bình thường.
And this is our volume.
Và đây là doanh số.
Our volume has settled kind of at a higher level.
Doanh số ổn định ở mức cao hơn.
Why is it a higher level?
Tại sao lại cao hơn?
Because some of the people who were persuaded by the lower price to try
Vì một số người mua thử vì giá rẻ
liked it enough that they repurchased again at full price.
thích sản phẩm và tiếp tục mua lại ngay cả khi nguyên giá
So one of the keys here is to say don't discount your price out of desperation.
Yếu tố chủ chốt là không nên giảm giá chỉ vì tuyệt vọng
But typically discount it if you need to to get
mà hãy giảm nếu bạn muốn thu hút mọi người
people to try you when you've got something new and interesting to say.
khi sản phẩm có những điểm mới mẻ và thú vị.
You've got actually a point of difference
Bạn thực sự có điểm khác biệt
that maybe they were unaware of.
mà người ta chưa biết đến.
And then you can combine pricing with your positioning, your branding,
Lúc đó bạn có thể kết hợp chiến lược giá với định vị, xây dựng thương hiệu,
and indeed your communication of that differentiation.
và sự khác biệt hóa.
So all in all, when we bring this to a close, pricing is complicated.
Nói tóm lại, chiến lược giá rất phức tạp.
But like most things we're discussing, we can unpack it.
Nhưng cũng tương tự các chủ đề khác, ta có thể bóc tách được.
We can break it down, and we can systematically
Ta có thể chia nó thành từng phần nhỏ
design pricing strategies.
để thiết kế được một chiến lược giá.
And then we can experiment to understand what works for us and what does not.
Và rồi ta có thể thử nghiệm xem chiến lược nào hiệu quả.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[NHẠC]